Finding Aid for Jerald F. terHorst papers, 1972-2008
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Jerald F. terHorst papers 1972-2008
TerHorst, Jerald F.
1 oversize folders
3.5 linear feet (in 4 boxes)
2012003 Aa 2 UAl
Jerald terHorst was a political reporter for the Detroit News and served as President Ford's first press secretary, before resigning in protest of the pardon of Richard Nixon. He also wrote a biography Gerald Ford and a history of Air Force One. The collection includes correspondence, speeches, newspaper articles by terHorst and about him, audiotapes, and video documenting his role in the Gerald Ford administration and his later literary and public career.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
This collection was donated by Karen terHorst-Morris and Peter R. terHorst (donor no. 10559 ) in several accessions between 2011 and 2014.
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Jerald F. terHorst was born on July 11, 1922 in Grand Rapids, MI. He received his bachelor's degree from the University of Michigan in 1947. After serving in the Marine Corps during World War II, he worked as a reporter for the Grand Rapids Press and the Detroit News. He started as a local political reporter covering Gerald Ford in Grand Rapids, but was eventually promoted to Washington Bureau Chief for the Detroit News in 1961.
Jerald F. terHorst was appointed as White House Press Secretary by President Ford in August of 1974, following Richard Nixon's resignation. He served for a month before resigning in protest as a matter of conscience following the President's pardon of Nixon, who had never been charged with commission of a crime. TerHorst felt strongly that, in the United States, no one person is above the law. As he writes in his letter of resignation, he would be troubled by having to defend President Ford's action when Nixon's aides and Vietnam War draft evaders, who were charged with crimes and even imprisoned, were not afforded a similar pardon. Reflecting later about his resignation, terHorst offered additional reasons, including his presumed lack of credibility with the press after having denied the possibility of a pardon in the weeks leading up to September 8, 1974.
Following his resignation he returned to the Detroit News as a national affairs columnist. In 1981, he joined Ford Motor Company as their director of public affairs in Washington. He also served on the Advisory Council for the National Press Foundation and as a Gridiron Foundation President and Chairman.
Since 1974, terHorst has participated in many public lectures and roundtables to discuss the pardon of Richard Nixon and his resignation as White House Press Secretary, including appearances on Washington Week and NPR's All Things Considered. He also authored a monograph Gerald Ford and the Future of the Presidency (1974) and co-authored with Ralph Albertazzie The Flying White House: The Story of Air Force One (1979). TerHorst also was involved in production and was interviewed for two documentaries on the history of Air Force One: Air Force One: the Planes and the Presidents (Elliott Sluhan Productions, 1984) and Air Force One: Flight II, the Planes and the Presidents (Elliott Sluhan Productions, 1991).
TerHorst passed away on March 31, 2010 in North Carolina.
The Jerald F. terHorst Collection is arranged in six series: Biographical; Literary Career and Speaking Engagements; White House Press Secretary Detroit News Correspondent; Documentaries; and Audio-Visual Materials.
Subjects:
Air Force One (Presidential aircraft); Detroit news.; Ford, Gerald R., 1913-2006.; Gridiron Club (Washington, D.C.); Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-1994.; Presidential press secretaries--United States.; TerHorst, Jerald F.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Air Force One (Presidential aircraft); Carter, Jimmy, 1924-; Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald), 1917-1963.; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-1994.; Presidential press secretaries--United States.; TerHorst, Jerald F.
Subjects - Sound Recordings:
Air Force One (Presidential aircraft); Presidential press secretaries--United States.; TerHorst, Jerald F.; Sound recordings.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Slides.; Sound recordings.; Videotapes.
- Biographical
  The Biographical series (0.75 linear feet) includes material related to terHorst's service in the military (enlistment and discharge papers, military orders, correspondence related to his work at the Marine Corps Gazette) and articles about him. The series documents terHorst's involvement with various organizations and his membership on various boards, most notably, the as Chairman of the Gridiron Foundation. Also found here is information relating to various honors and awards given to terHorst, including the establishment of the Jerald F. terHorst Award for Excellence in Political Reporting at George Washington University's Graduate School of Political Management and School of Media and Public Affairs.
  - Articles about terHorst 1970s-2008 (Box 1)
    (most dated 1970s)
  - Boards and Organizations
    - Graduate School of Political Management 1989-1993 (Box 1)
    - Gridiron Foundation
      - Annual meeting and reports 1986-2003 (with gaps), 3 folders (Box 1)
      - Board of Trustees meetings 1977, 1980-1985 (Box 1)
      - Gridiron Club Dinner 1981-1993 (scattered), 2007 (Box 1)
      - Histories of the Foundation 1973-1985 (Box 1)
      - Records
        - 1987-1991 (Box 1)
        - 1994-2003 (with gaps) (Box 1)
      - Scholarship 1986-2003 (with gaps) (Box 1)
    - Handgun Control, Inc. 1999-2001 (Box 1)
    - Washington Journalism Center 1990-1992 (Box 1)
    - WETA (Greater Washington Educational Telecommunications Association) 1990-1999 (Box 1)
  - Honors and Awards
    - Association of White House Press Secretaries 1982, black-and-white photographs (Box 1)
    - Association of White House Press Secretaries certificate 1982 (Box 1)
    - Bristol Area Chamber of Commerce 1972 (Box 1)
    - Civil Liberties Award 1974 (Box 1)
    - Jerald F. TerHorst Award for Excellence in Political Journalism 1995-1997 (Box 1)
    - Norwich University Honorary Degree (Box 1)
    - State News Hall of Fame 2006 (Box 1)
  - Marine Corps 1943-1955
    - Marine Corps Gazette (Box 1)
    - Military papers (Box 1)
    - Orders (Box 1)
  - Retirement 1990 (Box 1)
- Literary Career and Speaking Engagements
  The Literary Career and Speaking Engagements (0.5 linear feet) series documents terHorst's work as an author and public speaker in the years following his resignation as White House Press Secretary. This series is largely comprised of materials relating to Flying White House: The Story of Air Force One, which terHorst co-authored with Ralph Albertazzie. Also included in the series is a small collection terHorst's notes and talking points on index cards.
  - Articles by terHorst, national press 1975-1980 (Box 1)
  - Authors Guild correspondence 1995-1995 (Box 1)
  - Economic Club of Detroit 1972 (Box 1)
  - Flying White House
    - Agreements and contracts 1976 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence 1978-1979 (Box 1)
    - Ralph Albertazzie notes 1977-1978 (Box 1)
    - Reviews 1979 (Box 1)
  - Keedick Lecture Bureau 1979-1980 (Box 1)
  - Leigh Bureau 1974-1975 (Box 1)
  - Speaking Engagements (post-resignation)
    - 1974-1996, includes black-and-white photograph (Box 1)
    - Notes and talking points undated (Box 1)
  - "The American Presidency: Its Power and Politics" lecture transcript July 30, 1976 (Box 2)
  - Third Press bankruptcy 1974-1979, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Universal Press Syndicate 1976 (Box 2)
- White House Press Secretary
  White House Press Secretary (0.25 linear feet) includes copies of congratulatory letters received by terHorst following his appointment and press clippings discussing his resignation.
  - Clippings 1974-2001 (Box 2)
  - Congratulatory correspondence (answered) August 1974, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Congratulatory correspondence (unanswered) August 1974, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Lee Baker correspondence 1991 (Box 2)
- Detroit News Correspondent
  The Detroit News Correspondent series (0.5 linear feet including 2 slide carousels and boxed slides; and an oversize folder) includes material related to terHorst's trips in his capacity as the Detroit News foreign and Washington correspondent. Of special interest are the visual materials included in this series: color slides with images from terHorst's European trip in advance of the 1959 Geneva Summit; color slides depicting John F. Kennedy's 1963 visit to Berlin; color slides and mostly black-and-white photographs from President Nixon's 1972 visit to China; and President Carter's 1978 trip to Africa. The series also includes Detroit News articles written by terHorst in 1959 and 1972.
  - Articles by terHorst 1954-1955, 1957, 1964, 1971-1972, 1981 (Box 2)
  - China trip
    - Economic Club speech 1972 (Box 2)
    - Retrospectives 1994, 2002 (Box 2)
    - Detroit News articles by terHorst covering the trip, 1972 (Folder 1)
  - Yugoslavia (1959 European tour) (Box 2)
  - Visual materials
    - Berlin color slides special by Press and Information Office of the Federal Government of Germany 1963, 28 slides (in 1 box) (Box 2)
    - Jimmy Carter in Africa May 1978, 32 slides (in 2 boxes) (Box 2)
    - European trip in advance of summit "Geneva Talks," 1959, 1 boxes
      - Europe, 98 slides (Box 2)
      - Israel, 76 slides (Box 2)
      - Paris, 29 slides (Box 2)
    - John F. Kennedy in Berlin June 1963, 73 slides (in 2 boxes) (Box 2)
    - Richard Nixon in China February 1972
      - Black-and-white photographs (Box 2)
      - Color group photograph, outsize (Folder 1)
      - February 21-28, 69 slides (Box 2)
      - Great Wall and Hawaii (after leaving China), 73 slides (Box 2)
- Documentaries
  The Documentaries series (1 linear foot) is dedicated to two Elliot Sluhan Productions documentaries (Air Force One: the Planes and the Presidents, 1984 and Air Force One: Flight II -- The Planes and the Presidents, 1991). Material includes correspondence and personal notes exchanged between terHorst and Elliot Sluhan, and offices of the former Secretary of State Henry Kissinger, Presidents Nixon, Carter, Reagan, then Vice-President George Bush, and other dignitaries. Also found here are scripts, publicity material and photographs, and reviews of the documentaries. The series also includes both documentaries on VHS and U-matic tapes.
  - Air Force One: the Planes and the Presidents, 1984
    - New Air Force One -- on All Things Considered (NPR) April 1, 1986 (audio cassette) (Box 3)
    - Air Force One: The Planes and the Presidents (PBS version), 1984 (1 U-matic videotape) (Box 3)
    - Correspondence 1982-1986, 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Photographs (Box 3)
      (2 black-and-white and 1 color)
    - Reviews (Box 3)
    - Scripts, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Air Force One: Flight II -- The Planes and the Presidents, 1991
    - Air Force One: Flight II..., (c)1984 (c)1989 (1 VHS and 1 U-matic videotape) (Box 3)
    - Correspondence
      - 1987-1991, 5 folders (Box 3)
      - 1994, 1997 (Box 3)
      - White House 1986-1990 (Box 3)
    - Premiere May 29, 1991 (Box 3)
    - Publicity photographs (Box 3)
      (1 black-and-white, 1 color)
- Audio-Visual Materials
  (see also the Documentaries series)
  - Audio cassettes
    The Audio-Visual Materials series (0.5 linear feet) includes audiotapes with recordings of interviews and lectures given by terHorst, and videotapes of lectures and roundtables featuring terHorst.
    - Chautauqua Institution (Box 4)
      - Lecture July 26, 1976 (Box 4)
      - Lecture July 27, 1976 (Box 4)
      - Lecture July 28, 1976 (Box 4)
      - Lecture July 29, 1976 (Box 4)
      - Lecture July 30, 1976, 2 audiocassettes (Box 4)
    - Norwich University May 21, 1977 (Box 4)
    - Panama Trip June 15, 1978 (Box 4)
    - Westinghouse try-out 1977 (Box 4)
  - Videotapes
    - 25 Years of the Presidency (UC San Diego), November 11, 1987 (VHS) (Box 4)
    - C-SPAN February 16, 1987 (VHS) (Box 4)
    - President Ford's Pardon of Richard Nixon -- A 25 Year Retrospective (Duquesne University), November 12, 1999 (VHS) (Box 4)
    - The Presidency, the Press & the People (KPBS-TV, San Diego), 1990 (VHS) (Box 4)
    - Washington Week in Review -- Jerry terHorst piece (VHS) (Box 4)
    - Washington Week in Review -- Jerry terHorst Retirement Special (VHS) (Box 4)
Related Material
Additional Jerald F. terHorst papers have been deposited in the Gerald R. Ford Presidential Library, Ann Arbor, Michigan.